<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true narration of the entertainment of his Royall Maiestie, from the time of his departure from Edenbrough; till his receiuing at London with all or the most speciall occurrences. Together with the names of those gentlemen whom his Maiestie honoured with knighthood.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06701</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17153</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108301</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843962</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843962</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8733</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06701)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8733)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 850:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true narration of the entertainment of his Royall Maiestie, from the time of his departure from Edenbrough; till his receiuing at London with all or the most speciall occurrences. Together with the names of those gentlemen whom his Maiestie honoured with knighthood.</title>
                  <author>T. M., fl. 1603, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Creede, for Thomas Millington,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed "T.M.", which probably represents the publisher's name. Sometimes erroneously attributed to Thomas Middleton.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-F⁴ G² .</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: His Maiesties entertainment from Scotland to London.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  I, --  King of England, 1566-1625.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8733:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8733:1"/>
            <p>THE True Narration of the Entertainment of his Royall Maieſtie, from the time of his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from <hi>Edenbrough;</hi> till his receiuing at London: with all or the moſt ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Occurrences. <hi>Together with the names of thoſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men whom his Maieſtie honoured with Knighthood.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Thomas Creede, featuring the crowned, female figure of Truth being scourged by a hand emerging from a cloud (McKerrow 299)</figDesc>
               <p>VIRESSIT VULNERE VERITAS</p>
               <p>TC</p>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by Thomas Creede, for Thomas Millington. 1603.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:8733:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8733:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter long trauell, to bee informed of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery particular, as much as diligence might preuaile in; this ſmall worke of his Maieſties Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and royall En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment is brought forth which though it may ſeeme to haue bene too long deferred, yet ſeeing nothing therof hath bene publike; no time can be too late, to expreſſe ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent a matter; wherein the dutifull loue of many noble Subiects ſo manifeſtly appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to our dread Lord and Soueraigne: and his Royall thankfulnes in exchange for that, which was indeed but dutie: though ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned with munificent bounty, that moſt houſes where his Highneſſe reſted, were ſo
<pb facs="tcp:8733:3"/>furniſhed by the owners, with plenty of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and delicates, that there was diſcerned no negligence; but if there were any offence, the ſinne only appeared in exceſſe; as more at large you ſhal hereafter perceiue: where the truth of euery thing is rather pointed at, than ſtood vpon.</p>
            <p>All diligence was vſed to get the names of thoſe Gentlemen, that in ſundry places receiued the honor of Knighthood, &amp; what the Heraldes haue in regiſter, are duly ſet downe, both for name, time, and place. If any be omitted, let it pleaſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie their names, and the houſe where they receiued that honor; and there ſhall be addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions put to this Empreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; or at leaſt (which wil be by order more fitly) placed in the next Many I am ſure there are not miſſing, and only in that point we are ſomewhat doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: the reſt is from his Highneſſe departure from <hi>Edenbrough:</hi> his comming to <hi>London,</hi> ſo exactly ſet downe, as nothing can be added to it, but ſuperfluous words; which we haue ſtriued to auoyd.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine T. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:8733:3"/>
            <head>A NARRATION of the Progreſſe and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment of the Kings moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Maieſtie, with the occurrents <hi>happening in the ſame iourney.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE eternall maieſtie, in whoſe hand are both the meane and mightie of the earth, pleaſed to deliuer from weakeneſſe of body and griefe of minde, <hi>Elizabeth</hi> his hand-maide, our late Royall Miſtreſſe &amp; gracious Soueraigne, eaſing her age from the burthen of earthly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, &amp; placing her (as we ſtedfaſtly hope) in his heauenly Empire, beeing the reſting place after death, for all them that beleeue faithfully in their life.</p>
            <p>Thurſday the 24. of March, ſome two houres after midnight, departed the ſpirit of that great Princeſſe, from the priſon of her weake body, which now ſleepes in the Sepulchre of her Grand-father.</p>
            <p>The Counſell of State, and the Nobilitie, on
<pb facs="tcp:8733:4"/>whom the care of all the country chiefly depended, immediately aſſembling together, (no doubt aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with the ſpirit of truth) conſidering the infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble right of our Soueraigne Lord King <hi>Iames,</hi> tooke ſuch order, that the newes of the Queenes death ſhould no ſooner be ſpread, to deiect the hearts of the people; but at the inſtant they ſhould be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted with the proclaiming of the King.</p>
            <p>Being hereon determined, Sir <hi>Robert Carie</hi> tooke his iourney in poſte towards <hi>Scotland,</hi> to ſignifie to the Kings Maieſtie the ſad tidings of his Royall ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters death, and the ioyfull hearts of his ſubiects that expected no comfort but in and by his Maieſties bleſſed gouernment.</p>
            <p>This noble Gentlemans care was ſuch, that he intermitted no time, but notwithſtanding his ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry ſhift of horſes, and ſome falles that bruiſed him very ſore, he by the way proclaimed the king at <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth.</hi> And on ſaterday comming to <hi>Barwick,</hi> acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his worthy brother Sir <hi>Iohn Carie</hi> how al things ſtood, poaſted on to <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> where he attained that night, hauing ridden neare three hundre miles in leſſe then three dayes.</p>
            <p>But before we come there, you ſhall vnderſtand what was inſtantly done at <hi>Barwick</hi> by ſir <hi>Iohn Carie,</hi> vpon the newes brought by Sir <hi>Robert</hi> his brother: who like a worthy ſouldier, &amp; politike Stateſman, conſidering it was a Towne of great import, and a place of warre, he cauſed all the Garriſon to be ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned together, as alſo the Mayor, Aldermen, and Burgeſſes, in whoſe preſence he made a ſhort and pythie Oration, including her Maieſties death, and
<pb facs="tcp:8733:4"/>ſignifying the intent of the State, for ſubmitting to their lawfull Lord. And preſently with great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment of all parties, his Maieſtie was proclaimed King of <hi>England, Scotland, France, &amp;c.</hi> on Saterday in the afternoone, being the 26. of March, about three of the clocke. Where all the people (though they grieued for their late Queene) yet was griefe ſuddenly turned to pleaſure, in expectation of their new King. But we will poſte from <hi>Barwick</hi> after Sir <hi>Robert Carey,</hi> and ouertake him at <hi>Edenburgh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You vnderſtood before, that Sir <hi>Robert</hi> came to <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgh</hi> on Saterday night, where being admitted to the King, be-bloodied with great falles &amp; bruſes, brought his Highneſſe the firſt newes of Queene <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeths</hi> death; which howſoeuer it preſented him with kingdoms, glory, &amp; immenſiue wealth; yet like his Royal ſelfe he ſhewed apparant ſignes of Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſorrow. And diſmiſſing Sir <hi>Robert Carie</hi> after ſo great toile to his repoſe, his Maieſtie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued in his griefe, and through that expreſſed his true pietie.</p>
            <p>It was thought neceſſarie in ſo high affaires to let ſlip no occaſion how euer ſorrow particularly tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched his Maieſtie for the loſſe of his priuate friend, and Royal ſiſter: yet the general care as wel of thoſe his people in <hi>Scotland,</hi> as for vs in <hi>Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,</hi> cauſed him on Sunday, being the 27. of March to diſpatch the Biſhop of <hi>Halirud-houſe</hi> to <hi>Barwick,</hi> that he might receiue the Towne to his vſe, as the neareſt place wherein by right hee claymed poſſeſſion. Who accordingly making all the ſpeede hee might, came to <hi>Barwick,</hi> where of the Gouernour hee was honourably entertained: and after ſignifying
<pb facs="tcp:8733:5"/>his maieſties pleaſure, repoſed himſelfe for that night.</p>
            <p>On Monday, being the 28. of March, by ſound of trumpet, the Gouernour, Mayor, Officers, and Counſell of the Towne, were aſſembled at the Croſſe, where there the Gouernour ſurrendered to the Biſhop of <hi>Halirud houſe</hi> his ſtaffe, and all his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie vnto the Kings Maieſties vſe: ſo likewiſe did the Mayor deliuer vp the keyes of the Towne. And the ſaide Biſhop being thus ſeized of all the authoritie to the Kings Maieſtie vſe, miniſtred the oath of alleageance, vnto the Gouernour, Mayor, and the ſuperiour Officers belonging to the Garriſon and to the Towne. Which oath taken, the Biſhop of <hi>Halirud-houſe,</hi> expreſſing the graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous intention of his Maieſtie, as well to them, as all other his ſubiects of <hi>England,</hi> whom hee found like them affected: which was rather to maintaine then to infringe their Charters; to giue, then take from them any thing; redeliuered the keyes and ſtaffe of authoritie to the Mayor and Gouernour: ſo likewiſe to euery Commaunder, Captaine, Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, and whatſoeuer office they had before her Maieſties death, there in the Kings name he confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them, to their great ioy &amp; contentment. Thus ſpent the Lord of <hi>Halirud-houſe</hi> the firſt part of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day in <hi>Barwick,</hi> and dyned with the Magiſtrates.</p>
            <p>In the afternoone the Lord Gouernour, and his chiefe Officers of place, called together all the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers that were vnder pay: ſo did the Mayor and Aldermen conuene all the Communaltie of the Towne: to whom when the oath was read, and the
<pb facs="tcp:8733:5"/>Magiſtrates had certified them that they had beene their example, the L. of <hi>Halyrud-houſe</hi> wondered at, and much commended their ioy and readineſſe to be ſworne ſeruants to ſo regall a Maiſter; which he amply diſcourſed to his Maieſtie at his returne to <hi>Edenburgh</hi> the next day, not hyding any of their forward applauſes, but deliuered their willingneſſe to his Highneſſe with expreſſe and liuely words: aſſuring him by his entrance into <hi>England</hi> at that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle doore, how welcome into the wide houſe his Excellence ſhould be.</p>
            <p>While this was a doing in <hi>Barwick,</hi> there drew to the King hourely moſt of the Nobilitie in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> with ſundry Knights and Gentle-men, gratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating the great bleſſings befallen his Highneſſe, and attending his Royall pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Beſides many numbers of Gentlemen came out of <hi>England</hi> to ſalute his Maieſtie, all whom he gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly welcommed, and honoured one of them with the Order of Knight-hood, being M. <hi>Iohn Pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> ſonne to Sir <hi>Iohn Paiton</hi> Lieutenant of the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> this being to that noble Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man no little glory that he was the firſt Knight (yea, named by the Kings Maieſtie himſelfe, his firſt Knight) that was made by our Soueraigne after he was nominated and truly knowne to bee the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt king in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>During the continuance of his Maieſtie in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> before his Progreſſe towardes <hi>England,</hi> his whole care was for the peaceable gouernment of of that realme, from which he was a while to part. And to that end, he had ſundry conferences with
<pb facs="tcp:8733:6"/>his Nobilitie, laying the ſafeſt proiects that in his wiſedome and their experiences ſeemed likely for effecting his royall deſire; which God willing will come to paſſe to his great liking and benefite of both the Realmes.</p>
            <p>But that it might more to his people appeare, he in perſon came graciouſly to the Citie of <hi>Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> vnto the publike Sermon: and after the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon was finiſhed, in a moſt learned, but more lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Oration, he expreſt his occaſion of leauing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to the Burgeſſes &amp; a number of the people: exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to contiune in obedience, being the bond that binde Princes to affect their ſubiects, which broken on their part he truſted ſhould neuer be, and of his they were aſſured: perſwading them alſo to agreement amongſt themſelues, being the bond of charitie that tyed all men (eſpecially Chriſtians) to loue and beare one with another. In which obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to him, and agreement amongſt themſelues if they continued, howſoeuer, he was in a manner at that time conſtrained to leaue them: yet hee would in his owne perſon viſite them, &amp; that ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in times conuenient, and moſt neceſſarie for his owne aduancement and their benefite.</p>
            <p>Yet for all his kingly Oratorie, milde behauiour and true intention, the peoples hearts againſt his departure were euen dead, and griefe ſeized euery priuate mans raynes, ſauing onely thoſe that were made happy by attending his Royall perſon into <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For now they began duly to thinke vpon his vnmatched vertues, which neuer the moſt malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:8733:6"/>enemie could impeach, being in the worlds eie innocent of any capitall and notorious crime, but ſuch as may be incident to any iuſt man, who dayly fall, but neuer fall away: they now conſidered his affabilitie, mercie, iuſtice, and magnanimitie: they remembred how in late yeares <hi>Scotland</hi> by his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment had increaſed in more riches, then in the time of many his Predeceſſors. Beſides, his care for eſtabliſhing true Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, his Traffique almoſt with al Nations, the royaltie of his marriage, the bleſſings hoped for by his iſſue. And ſuch an vniuerſall ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row was amongſt them, that ſome of the meaner ſort ſpake euen diſtractedly: and none but at his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting (which yet we are not come vnto) expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſuch ſorrow, as in that Nation hath ſeldome bin ſeen the like: albeit the Kings Maieſtie was poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of that which the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſort of the Nation long wiſhed for, I meane the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>The 31. of March, being Thurſday, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie with great ſolemnitie and pompe, was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed King of <hi>England, Scotland, Fraunce</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> at the Market Croſſe of <hi>Edenbrugh,</hi> in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the whole Officers of Eſtate of the Realm, and many of the Nobilitie of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſundry Knights and Gentlemen of <hi>England.</hi> And in the euening of that day, there were many hundreds of Bonefires made all about the Citie, with great fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and merriment held, till the appearing of the next day.</p>
            <p>But as ioyfull as they were of his Maieſties great aduauncement and enlarging of his Empire, ſo were they (as I before noted) for their priuate
<pb facs="tcp:8733:7"/>want of him no leſſe filled with griefe, as aboue all other times was moſt apparantly expreſſed at his departure from <hi>Edenburgh</hi> towards <hi>England:</hi> the cries of poore people being ſo lamentable and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, that it moued his Maieſtie to much compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: yet ſeeing their clamors was only of affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not grounded on reaſon, with many graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and louing words he left them, and proceeded on his Progreſſe.</p>
            <p>It was the fift of April, being Tueſday, that his Maieſtie departed from <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> gallantly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with multitudes of his Nobility, Lords, Barons, and Gentlemen of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſome French, as the French Ambaſſadour, being Leger in <hi>Scotland,</hi> (whoſe wife was carried betwixt <hi>Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> and <hi>London</hi> by eight pioners or porters, one foure to relieue the other foure by turnes, carrying her in a chare with ſlings) as alſo his Maieſtie being accompanied with his own attendants, as the Duke of <hi>Lennox,</hi> the Earle of <hi>Argyle,</hi> the Earle of <hi>Murrey,</hi> the Earle of <hi>Casſils,</hi> the Earle of <hi>Mar,</hi> the Lorde <hi>Home,</hi> the Lord <hi>Oliphant,</hi> and ſundry other too te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious in this place to bee repeated: for that their ſeuerall names ſhall hereafter bee more particularly expreſſed. Beſides there were in his Highnes traine many numbers of gallant and well appointed Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Knights and Genlemen, who attended his Maieſtie that day from <hi>Edenburgh</hi> vnto <hi>Dunglaſſe,</hi> a houſe of the Lord <hi>Homes,</hi> where his Excellence repoſed himſelfe that night.</p>
            <p>Wedneſday the ſixt of April, his Maieſtie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed from <hi>Dunglaſſe</hi> towards <hi>Barwicke,</hi> hauing
<pb facs="tcp:8733:7"/>then attending on him many more Noblemen, Knights, and Gentlemen, beſides the Lords War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of the borders of <hi>England</hi> &amp; <hi>Scotland,</hi> attended by the Borderers with ſeuerall companies to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him. The Lord Gouernour of <hi>Barwick</hi> alſo being accompained with al the Counſell of warre: the Conſtables with their Cornets of horſe, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of the Captaines: the band of Gentlemen Penſioners, with diuers Gentlemen, aduanced for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to entertaine &amp; conduct his Maieſtie into the Towne of <hi>Barwick.</hi> Happy day, when peaceably ſo many warlike Engliſh gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to bring in an Engliſh &amp; Scottiſh king, both included in one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, into that towne that many a 100. years hath bin a town of the enemie, or at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt, held in all leagues either for one Nation or the other. But the King of peace haue glory, that ſo peaceably hath ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, a King deſcended from the Royall blood of either Nation, to make that Towne by his poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it, a harbour for Engliſh and Scots, without thought of wrong or grudging enuie.</p>
            <p>Not to digreſſe longer, theſe Gallants met him, and were graciouſly reſpected of his Highneſſe, ſo falling in among the other Trophees, they ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; and when his Highneſſe came within ſome halfe mile of the Towne, and began to take viewe thereof, it ſuddenly ſeemed like an inchanted Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle: for from the mouthes of dreadfull engins, not long before full fed by moderate atteſ-men, that knew how to ſtop and emptie the braſſe and iron panches of thoſe roring noiſes, came ſuch a tempeſt, as dreadfull and ſometimes more deathfull then thunder, that all the ground thereabout trembled,
<pb facs="tcp:8733:8"/>as in an earthquake, the houſes and towers ſtagge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, wrapping the whole Towne in a mantle of ſmoake, wherein the ſame was a while hid from the ſight of his Royall owner.</p>
            <p>But nothing violent can be permanent, it was too hote to laſt, &amp; yet I haue heard it credibly reported, that a better peale of Ordinance was neuer in any fouldiers memorie (and there are ſome olde King <hi>Harries</hi> Lads in <hi>Barwicke</hi> I can tell you) diſcharged in that place: neither was it very ſtrange; for no man can remember <hi>Barwick</hi> honoured with the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of ſo powerfull a Maiſter.</p>
            <p>Well, the King is now very neere the gates: and as all darkneſſe flyes before the face of the Sunne, ſo did theſe clouds of ſmoake and gun-powder vaniſh at his gracious approach. In the clearnes of which faire time, iſſued out of the towne, M. <hi>William Selbie,</hi> Gentleman, Porter of <hi>Barwick,</hi> with diuers Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of good repute: and humbling himſelf before the kings Maieſtie, preſented vnto him the keyes of all the Ports, who receiued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> graciouſly: &amp; when his Highnes was entred betwixt the gates, he reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the ſaid M. <hi>Selbie</hi> the keyes againe, &amp; graced him with the honor of Knight-hood for this his eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeciall ſeruice: in that he was the firſt man that poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed his Excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of thoſe keyes: <hi>Barwick</hi> indeed being the gate that opened into all his Dominions.</p>
            <p>This done, his Highneſſe entred the ſecond gate, and being within both the walles, he was receiued by the Captaine of the ward, and ſo paſſed through a double gaurde of Souldiers, well armed in all points: but with lookes humble, and words cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, they gaue his Maieſtie to know, their hearts
<pb facs="tcp:8733:8"/>witneſſed that their armes were worne only to bee vſed in his Royall ſeruice.</p>
            <p>Betweene this gaurde, his Maieſtie paſſed on to the Market Croſſe, where the Maior and his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren receiued him with no ſmall ſignes of ioy, and ſuch ſignes of triumph as the breuitie of time for prepatation would admit. But the common people ſeemed ſo ouer-wrapt with his preſence, that they omitted nothing their power and capacities could attaine vnto, to expreſſe loyall dutie and heartie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: kneeling, ſhouting, (crying, welcome, and God ſaue King <hi>Iames,</hi> till they were (in a maner) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated to be ſilent.</p>
            <p>As ſoone as it pleaſed the people to giue him leaue that he might ſpeake, M. <hi>Parkinſon</hi> the Recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Barwick,</hi> beeing a man graue and reuerend, made a briefe ſpeech to his Maieſty, acknowledging him their ſole and Soueraigne Lord. To whom in the Townes name he ſurrendred their Charter, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting his Highneſſe alſo from them with a Purſe of gold, which as an offering of their loue he graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly receiued. And for their Charter, he anſwered them moſt bening and royally, that it ſhould bee continued, and that he would maintaine their Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges, and vphold them and their Towne in all equitie, by reaſon it was the principall and firſt place, honoured with his mightie and moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſon.</p>
            <p>Theſe ceremonies amongſt the Towneſ-men ended, as his vſuall manner is after any iourney, his Maieſty paſt to the Church, there to humble himſelfe before the exalter of the humble, and thanke him for the benefites beſtowed vpon him
<pb facs="tcp:8733:9"/>and all his people: at which time preached before him the Reuerend Father in God, Doctor <hi>Tobie Mathew,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> who made a moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and worthy Sermon; which finiſhed, the King departed to his Pallace, and then they gaue him a peale of great Ordinance, more hotte then before. <hi>Barwick</hi> hauing neuer had King to reſt within her walles welnie theſe hundreth yeares.</p>
            <p>The night was quickly ouerpaſt, eſpecially with the Towneſ-men that neuer in a night thought themſelues ſecurer; but the iourney of the houres are alwayes one, how euer they are made long or ſhort by the apprehenſion of ioy, or ſufferance of griefe. The mornings Sun chaſed away the clouds of ſleepe from euery eye, which the more willingly opened, that they might bee comforted with the ſight of their beloued Soueraigne, who in his Eſtate (attended vpon by the Gouernour and the Noble men, together with the Magiſtrates and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the Towne) paſſed to the Church, where he ſtayed the diuine prayers and Sermon; which, when with his wonted himilitie he had heard fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, in the like eſtate he returned to his Pallace.</p>
            <p>This day being Thurſday the 7. of April, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie aſcended the walles, whereupon all the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniers, and other Officers belonging to the great Ordinance ſtood, euery one in his place: the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines with their bands of ſouldiers likewiſe vnder their ſeuerall Colours. Amongſt which war-like traine, as his Maieſtie was very pleaſant and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſo to ſhew inſtance how he loued &amp; reſpected the Art-militarie, hee made a ſhot himſelfe out of a Canon, ſo faire, and with ſuch ſigne of experience,
<pb facs="tcp:8733:9"/>that the moſt expert Gunners there beheld it, not without admiration: and there was none of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment preſent, but without flattery gaue it iuſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation.</p>
            <p>Of no little eſtmation did the Gunners account the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in, after this kingly ſhot, but his Maieſty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue al vertues, in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perance moſt excellent, left that part of the wall &amp; their extraordinary applauſe: but being attended by his nobilitie both of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> (the Lord <hi>Henry Howard,</hi> brother to the late Duke of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Cobham</hi> being then newly come to the Towne) and guarded by the Gentlemen Penſioners of <hi>Barwick,</hi> he beſtowed this day in ſurueying of the plots and fortifications, commending the manner of the ſouldiers, and the militarie order of the Towne, being indeed one of the beſt places of ſtrength in all the North of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> All which, when with great liking he had to his kingly pleaſure beheld, he returned to his Pallace, and there repoſed till the next day.</p>
            <p>The 8. of Aprill being Fryday, the Trumpets warned for the remoue; and all that morning his Maieſtie with royall liberalitie beſtowed amongſt the Garriſon Souldiers, and euery Officer for warre according to his place, ſo rich and bounteous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, that all ſouldiers by his bountifull begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning there, may be aſſured they ſhall not (as they haue bin) be curtald of their duties by exacting pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, but vſed as the ſeruants and ſeruitors of a king: which very name, but more his largeſſe, addes dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpirit to a man of warre.</p>
            <p>After dinner his Highneſſe mounted on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe
<pb facs="tcp:8733:10"/>and tooke leaue of <hi>Barkicke,</hi> where neare the bridge, he Knighted M. <hi>Ralph Gray,</hi> a Gentleman of great commaund and poſſeſſion neare the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            <p>As his Excellence left <hi>Barwicke,</hi> and entered the Realme of <hi>England,</hi> he was receiued by M. <hi>Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Forester,</hi> high Shireffe of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> who beſides his owne ſeruants &amp; followers, was accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with a number of gallant Gentlemen of the ſhyre: who riding before his Maieſtie, led the way towards <hi>Withrington,</hi> where his Maieſtie intended to reſt that night.</p>
            <p>By the way, of his Kingly goodneſſe, and Royall inclination to the honor of armes, and reuerence of vertuous age, he vouchſafed to viſit that worthy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable ſouldier, Sir <hi>William Read,</hi> who being blind with age, was ſo comforted with the preſence and gracious ſpeeches of the king, that his ſpirits ſeemed ſo powerfull within him, as he boaſted himſelfe to feele the warmth of youth ſtirre in his froſt-nipt bloud.</p>
            <p>The way his Maieſtie had to ride being long, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced him to ſtay with this good Knight the leſſe while; but that litle time was ſo comfortable, that his friends hope it wil be a meane to cheriſh the old knight all his life long. Not to be longer writing this, then his Highneſſe was riding the iourney: he departed thence vpon the ſpurre, ſcarce any of his traine being able to keepe him company: for being neare 37. miles, he rode it al in leſſe then foure houres. And by the way for a note, the miles accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Northren phraſe, are a wey-bit longer
<pb facs="tcp:8733:10"/>then they be here in the South.</p>
            <p>Well, as long as the miles were, his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie made ſhort worke, and attained <hi>Withrington,</hi> where by the maiſter of the place, Sir <hi>Robert Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> and his right vertuous Lady, hee was recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with all dutie and affection, the houſe being plentifully furniſhed for his entertainment. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, for ſcituation and pleaſure, it ſtands very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull.</p>
            <p>His Maieſtie hauing a little while repoſed himſelfe after his great iourney, found new oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to trauell further: for as he was delighting himſelfe with the pleaſure of the Parke, hee ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly beheld a number of Deere neare the place: The game being ſo faire before him, hee could not forbeare, but according to his wonted maner, forth he went, and ſlew two of them. Which done, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned with a good appetite to the houſe, where hee was moſt royally feaſted and banketted that night.</p>
            <p>On Saterday the 9. of Aprill, his Maieſtie prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red towards <hi>New-castle.</hi> But before his departure from <hi>Withrington,</hi> he Knighted M. <hi>Henry Withring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> M. <hi>William Fenicke,</hi> and M. <hi>Edward Gorge.</hi> After which taking his leaue with Royall curteſie, he ſet forwards towards <hi>New-castle,</hi> being 16. miles from <hi>Withrington.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To paſſe the occurrentes by the way, being not very materiall, when his Maieſtie drew neare to <hi>New-castle,</hi> the Mayor, Aldermen, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and beſt Commoners of the ſame, beſide num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of other people, in ioyfull manner met him.
<pb facs="tcp:8733:11"/>The Mayor preſenting him with the ſword and keyes with humble dutie and ſubmiſſion. Which his Highneſſe graciouſly accepting, he returned them againe: Giuing alſo to his Maieſtie in token of their loue and heartie loyaltie, a purſe full of Gold. His Maieſtie giuing them full power and authoritie vnder him, as they lately held in her Maieſties name: Ratifying all their cuſtomes and priuiledges that they were poſſeſſed of, and had a long time held. And ſo paſſing on, hee was conducted to the Mayors houſe, where he was richly entertained, and remained there three dayes.</p>
            <p>Vpon Sunday, being the 10. of Aprill, his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie went to the Church, before whom the Biſhop of <hi>Durham</hi> preached. And that day, (as it is his moſt Chriſtian-like cuſtome) being ſpent in deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he reſted till Munday, which he beſtowed in viewing the Towne, the manner and beautie of the bridge and keye, being one of the faireſt in all the North parts. Beſides, he releaſed all priſoners, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thoſe that lay for treaſon, murther and Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie, giuing great ſummes of money for the releaſe of many that were impriſoned for debt. Who hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily praiſed God and bleſſed his Maieſtie for their vnexpected libertie.</p>
            <p>So ioyfull were the Towneſmen of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> of his Maieſtie there being, that they thankfully bare all charge of his houſehold, during the time of his abode with them, being from Saterday till VVed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſday morning. All things were in ſuch plentie, and ſo delicate for varietie, that it gaue great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment
<pb facs="tcp:8733:11"/>to his Maieſtie. And on the Towneſmens parts there was nothing but willingneſſe appeared, ſaue onely at his Highneſſe departure, but there was no remedie. Hee hath yet many of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by his preſence to comfort, and forward no doubt hee will, as he thence did, giuing thankes to them for theyr loyall and heartie affection. And on the bridge before hee came at <hi>Gateſide,</hi> hee made M. <hi>Robert Dudley</hi> Mayor of <hi>New-castle,</hi> Knight.</p>
            <p>This VVedneſday being the 13. of Aprill, his Maieſtie ſet forwarde towarde <hi>Durham.</hi> And at <hi>Gateſide</hi> neare <hi>New-caſtle,</hi> hee was met by the Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe of the Countie, and moſt of the Gentlemen in the ſame.</p>
            <p>In his way neare <hi>Chester,</hi> a ſtreete, a litle Towne betwixt <hi>New-castle</hi> and <hi>Durham,</hi> he turned on the left hand of the Roade, to view a pleaſant Caſtle of the Lord <hi>Lumleyes,</hi> which being a goodly Aedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of free ſtone, built in quadrant maner, ſtands on the ſhoring of a hill in the middle of a greene, with a Riuer at the foote of it, &amp; woods about it on euery ſide: but to the Towneward which is by the Riuer, diuided from it.</p>
            <p>After his Highneſſe had a while delighted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with the pleaſure of the place, he returned on his way towards <hi>Durham,</hi> being ſixe miles from thence. Of which way he ſeldome makes long iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. And when he came neare, the Magiſtrates of the citie met him, &amp; behauing themſelues as others before them, it was by his Highneſſe as thankfully accepted. And paſſing through the gates, whence
<pb facs="tcp:8733:12"/>his Excellence entred the market place, there was an excellent Oration made vnto him, containing in effect the vniuerſall ioy conceiued by his ſubiects at his approach, being of power to diuert from them ſo great a ſorrow as had lately poſſeſſed them all. The Oration ended, he paſſed towards the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops houſe, where he was royally receiued. The Biſhop attending his Maieſtie with a hundred Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen in Tawny Liueries. Of all his entertainment in particular at the Biſhops, his merrie &amp; well ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ieſts, as wel there as in other parts of his iourny, all his words being of full waight, and his ieſts filled with the ſalt of wit, yet ſo facetious and pleaſant, as they were no leſſe gracious and worthy regard, then the words of ſo Royall a Maieſtie; it is bootleſſe to repeate them, they are ſo well knowne.</p>
            <p>Thurſday being the 14. day, his Maieſtie tooke leaue of the Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> whom he greatly graced and commended, for his learning, humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and grauitie, promiſing to reſtore diuers things taken from the Biſhoppricke, which he hath accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly in part done, giuing him alreadie poſſeſſion of <hi>Durham</hi> houſe in the Strand. In briefe, his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie left <hi>Durham,</hi> and remooued toward <hi>Walworth,</hi> being ſixteene miles from <hi>Durham.</hi> Where, by the Gentlewoman of the houſe, named Miſtreſſe <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſon,</hi> hee was ſo bountifully entertained, that it gaue his Excellence very high contentment. And after his quiet repoſe there that night, and ſome part of the next day, hee tooke his leaue of the Gentlewoman with many thankefull and Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gratulations, for her extending coſts in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment
<pb facs="tcp:8733:12"/>of him and his traine.</p>
            <p>Fryday being the 15. of Aprill, his Maieſtie ſet forward fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Miſtreſſe <hi>Geniſons</hi> of <hi>Walworth</hi> towards <hi>Yorke.</hi> His traine ſtill encreaſing by the numbers of Noblemen and Gentlemen from the South parts, that came to offer him fealtie, and to reioyce at his ſight: whoſe loue although he greatly tendered, yet did their multitudes ſo oppreſſe the countrey, and make prouiſion ſo deare, that he was faine to publiſh an Inhibition againſt the inordinate and dayly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of peoples comming, that many were ſtopt of their way, and onely thoſe that had affaires ſuffered to haue acceſſe, ſome of great name and office being ſent home to attend their places. All this notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, a number there were in his Highneſſe traine, ſtill encreaſing in euery ſhyre. For now the high Shireffe of <hi>Yorke</hi> ſhyre, gallantly accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, attended his Maieſtie to M. <hi>Inglebeyes</hi> beſide <hi>Topcliffe,</hi> being about 16. miles from <hi>Walworth,</hi> who with great ſubmiſſion receiued his Maieſtie, and there he reſted for that night.</p>
            <p>On Saterday being the ſixteenth of Aprill, his Maieſtie remoued from maiſter <hi>Inglesbeye</hi> towards <hi>Yorke,</hi> being ſixteene miles from <hi>Topcliffe:</hi> and when he came about ſome three miles from <hi>Yorke,</hi> (the liberties of the Citie extending ſo farre) maiſter <hi>Bucke</hi> and maiſter <hi>Robinſon,</hi> Shireffes of the Citie met him, &amp; with humble dutie preſented him with their white ſtaues: which his Maieſtie receiuing, hee deliuered them inſtantly againe, ſo they atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him towards the Citie; within a mile of which, when his Highneſſe approached, there mette
<pb facs="tcp:8733:13"/>him the Lorde <hi>Burleigh,</hi> Lorde Preſident of the North, with many worthy Knights and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the ſhyre. Theſe alſo attended on his perſon to <hi>Yorke.</hi> Where, when he came neare vnto the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, there met him three of the Sergeants at Armes, late ſeruants to the deceaſed Queene, viz. M. <hi>Wood,</hi> M. <hi>Damfort,</hi> and M. <hi>Weſtrope,</hi> who deliuered vp their Maces, which his Maieſtie with Royall curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, redeliuered to them, commaunding them to waite on him in their olde places, which preſently they did. And at the ſame time the Sergeant Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peter, with ſome other of his fellows, did in like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſubmit themſelues, and render their ſeruice, which he beningly accepted, &amp; commanded them in like maner to waite on him.</p>
            <p>Then rode he on till he came to one of the gates of <hi>Yorke;</hi> where the Lord Mayor of the Citie, the Aldermen, and the wealthieſt Commoners, with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of other people met him. There a long Oration being made, the Lord Mayor deliuered the Sword and Keyes to his Maieſtie, together with a Cup of Gold, filled full of Gold, which preſent his Maieſtie gratefully accepted, deliuering the Keyes againe to the Lord Mayor; but about the bearing of the Sword there was ſome ſmall contention, the Lorde Preſident taking it for his place, the Lorde Mayor of the Citie eſteeming it his. But to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide the doubt, the Kings Maieſtie merily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, If the Sword beeing his, they would not bee pleaſed, that hee ſhould haue the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thereof. Wherevnto when they humbly anſwered, it was all in his pleaſure, his Highneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:8733:13"/>deliuered the Sword to one, that knew wel how to vſe a ſword, hauing beene tryed both at Sea and on Shoare, the thriſe honoured Earle of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> who bare it before his Maieſtie; ryding in great State from the gate to the Minſter. In which way there was a Conduit that all the day long ran white and claret wine, euery man to drinke as much as he liſted.</p>
            <p>From the Minſter his Maieſtie went on foote to his owne houſe, being the Mannor of Saint <hi>Maries,</hi> hauing all the way a rich Canopie ouer his head, ſupported by foure Knights, and being brought thither he was honourably receiued by the Lorde <hi>Burleigh,</hi> who gaue cheerfull entertainment to all the followers of his Maieſtie during the time of his continuance in <hi>Yorke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 17. day beeing Sunday, his Maieſtie paſſed towards <hi>Yorke</hi> Minſter, being one of the goodlieſt Minſters in all the Land, <hi>England</hi> being as famous for Churches as any one kingdom in <hi>Europe,</hi> if they were kept in reparations as that Minſter is. To this Minſter the King paſſed to heare the Sermon, and at the gate a Coach was offered to his Highneſſe. But he graciouſly anſwered, <hi>I will haue no Coach, for the people are deſirous to ſee a King, and ſo they ſhall, for they shall aſwell ſee his body as his face.</hi> So to the great comfort of the people, he went on foote to the Church, &amp; there he heard the Sermon, which was preached by the Biſhop of <hi>Lymrick,</hi> whoſe doctrine and methode of teaching, was highly by his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie commended. And what his iudgement is, is as extant to vs all of any vnderſtanding, as the light of
<pb facs="tcp:8733:14"/>the cleare mid-day, or Sunne to euery perfect eye. The Sermon ended, his Maieſtie returned a foote in the ſame ſort as he came, to his Mannor, where he was Royally feaſted.</p>
            <p>This Sunday there was a Seminary Prieſt appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended: who before (vnder the title of a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man) had deliuered a Petition to his Maieſtie, in the name of all the Engliſh Catholikes; when he was taken, his Highneſſe had ſome conference with him: but by reaſon of other great affaires he refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him to be further examined by the Byſhop of <hi>Limbricke,</hi> who preſenting the effects of his exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, the Prieſt was the next day committed.</p>
            <p>Dinner being ended, his Maieſtie walked into the garden of the Pallace, being a moſt delightfull place: where there awaited him a number of Gentlemen of great name and worth: whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations he receiued from Honourable perſons, &amp; beheld honor charactred in their faces. For this is one eſpeciall note in his Maieſtie; Any man that hath ought with him, let him be ſure he haue a iuſt cauſe, for he beholdes all mens faces with ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and commonly the looke is the window for the heart. Well, to that I ſhould handle. Amongſt theſe Gentlemen, it pleaſed his Maieſtie to make choiſe of theſe following, whom he graced with the honour of Knight-hood.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Cecill.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Edmond Trasford.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Thomas Holcraft.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iohn Mallorie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Inglesbey.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Philip Conſtable.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Chriſtopher Haward.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Robert Swift.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:8733:14"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Richord worthley.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Henrie Bellouſeyes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Thomas Ferfax:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Henrie Griffith.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Francis Boynton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Henrie Cholmley.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Richard Gargraue.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Marmaduke Grimſtone.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Lancelote Alford.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Ralph Eliker.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir George Frauil.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Maior Vauaſor.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Ralph Babthorp.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Richard Londer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Walter Crape.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The ſame day, his Maieſtie cauſed fiue Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to be ſworn his ſeruants, which ſerued Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> before time, whoſe names were <hi>M. Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Connisbie, M. George Pollord,</hi> Vſhers: dayly wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. <hi>M. Thomas Rolles,</hi> and <hi>M. Hariffe,</hi> Gentlemen, quarter waiters: and <hi>M. Richard Read-head,</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Sewer, in ordinarie of his Maieſties Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
            <p>This day likewiſe, the Maior of <hi>Kingstone</hi> vpon <hi>Hull,</hi> deliuered to his Maieſtie a petition, which was alſo ſubſcribed and iuſtified by diuers Aldermen of the ſaid Towne, to be done in the behalfe of all the poore Inhabitants: who with one voyce beſought his Maieſtie, that they might be relieued and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coured, againſt the dayly ſpoiles done to them by thoſe of <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> that had long moleſted them, and other the Engliſh Coaſt-men. His Highneſſe, as he is naturally inclined to much pitie, ſo at that time hee ſeemed to haue great compaſſion of their wrongs and afflictions, which were not hidden from him, though they had beene ſilent: but he comforted them with this Princely and heroicke reply: <hi>That he would defend them: and no Dunkirkar
<pb facs="tcp:8733:15"/>should after dare to doe any of his ſubiects wrong.</hi> In which aſſurance they departed, and no doubt ſhall finde the effect of his kingly promiſe.</p>
            <p>I told you before what bounty the Lord <hi>Burleigh</hi> vſed, during the continuance of the kings Maieſtie in the Mannor: but it was indeed exceeding all the reſt in any place of <hi>England</hi> before, Buttries, Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and Sellars alwayes held open in great abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance for all commers.</p>
            <p>Munday being the 18. day, his Maieſtie was fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by the L. Maior of <hi>Yorke,</hi> whom he knighted by the name of Sir <hi>Robert Walter,</hi> at whoſe houſe there was ſuch plentie of all dilicates as could bee poſſibly deuiſed. After dinner, his Maieſtie follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the rule of mercy he had begun with, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all the priſoners to be ſet at libertie, except Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts &amp; wilfull murtherers. Which deed of charitie effected, he left <hi>Yorke;</hi> and rode to <hi>Grimſtone,</hi> being a houſe of <hi>Sir Edward Stanhops,</hi> where hee lay that night, and dined the next day, his Maieſtie and all his Traine hauing their moſt bountifull entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. All the Offices in the houſe ſtanding open for all commers, euery man without checke, eating and drinking at pleaſure. Before his Maieſtie depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from <hi>Grimſtone,</hi> he knighted theſe Gentlemen:
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir Roger Aſton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir Thomas Aſton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir Thomas Holt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir Iames Harington.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir Charles Montague.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir Thomas Dawney.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir william Bambro.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir Francis Louel.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir Thomas Gerret.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir Robert Walters</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Maior of Yorke.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir Ralph Conisbie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir Richard Muſgraue.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8733:15"/>
            <p>The 19. day being Tueſday, his Maieſtie tooke his iourney towards <hi>Doncaster,</hi> where by the way he went to <hi>Pomfret,</hi> to ſee the Caſtle, which when he had at pleaſure viewed, he tooke horſe and rode to <hi>Doncaster,</hi> where he lodged all night, at the ſigne of the bear, in an Inne, giuing the hoaſt of the houſe for his good entertainment, a Leaſe of a Mannor houſe in a reuerſion, of good value.</p>
            <p>The 20. day being Wedneſday, his Maieſtie rode towards <hi>Worſtop,</hi> the Noble Earle of <hi>Shrewſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buries</hi> houſe: &amp; at <hi>Batine,</hi> the high Shirife of <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> tooke his leaue of the King, and there M. <hi>Askoth,</hi> the high Shiriffe of <hi>Nottinghamſhire</hi> receiued him, being gallantly appointed both with horſe &amp; man. And ſo he conducted his Maieſtie on, till hee came within a mile of <hi>Blyth,</hi> where his Highneſſe lighted, and ſat downe on a banke ſide to eate and drinke.</p>
            <p>After his Maieſties ſhort repaſt, to <hi>Worſtop</hi> his Maieſtie rides forward, but by the way in the Parke he was ſomewhat ſtayed: for there appeared a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Hunteſ-men all in greene: the chiefe of which with a woodmans ſpeech did welcome him, offering his Maieſtie to ſhew him ſome game, which he gladly condiſcended to ſee: and with a traine ſet, he hunted a good ſpace, very much delighted; at laſt he went into the houſe, where he was ſo nobly receiued with ſuperfluitie of all things, that ſtill eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry entertainment ſeemed to exceed other. In this place, beſides the abundaunce of all prouiſion and delicacie, there was moſt excellent ſoule-rauiſhing muſique, wherewith his Highneſſe was not a little delighted.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8733:16"/>
            <p>At <hi>Worſtop</hi> he reſted on Wedneſday night, and in the morning ſtayed breakfaſt: which ended, there was ſuch ſtore of prouiſion left, of foule, fiſh, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt euery thing, beſides bread, beere, &amp; wine: that it was left open for any man that would, to come and take. After breakfaſt his Maieſtie prepared to remooue, but before his departure hee made theſe Gentlemen knights, whoſe names are following.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iohn Manners.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Henrie Gray.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Francis Newport.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Henrie Beaumont.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Edward Lockrane.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Hew Smith.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Edmond Lucie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Edmond Cokin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iohn Harper.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Damcort.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Henrie Perpoint.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Thomas Grisbey.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iohn Beeron.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Perciuall Willoughby.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Peter Freſchewell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Skipwirth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Richard Sexton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Thomas Stanley.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The 21. being Thurſday, his Highneſſe tooke his way towardes <hi>New-warke</hi> vpon <hi>Trent,</hi> where that night he lodged in the Caſtle; being his own houſe, where the Aldermen of <hi>New-warke</hi> preſented his Maieſtie with a faire gilt Cup, manifeſting their duties and louing hearts to him, which was very kindly accepted.</p>
            <p>In this towne and in the Court, was taken a Cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purſe doing the deed: and being a baſe pilfering theefe, yet was all Gentleman-like, in the out ſide: this fellow had good ſtore of Coyne found about him; and vpon his examination confeſſed that hee had from <hi>Barwick</hi> to that place, plaied the cut-purſe
<pb facs="tcp:8733:16"/>in the Court: his fellow was ill miſt, for no doubt hee had a walking mate: they drew togither like Coach-horſes, and it is pitie they did not hang togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for his Maieſtie hearing of this nimming gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, directed a Warrant, preſently to the Recorder of <hi>New-warke,</hi> to haue him hanged, which was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly executed. This bearing ſmal comfort to all the reſt of his pilfering facultie, that the firſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect that ſuffered death in <hi>England,</hi> in the raigne of King <hi>Iames,</hi> was a Cut-purſe, which fault if they amend not, heauen ſodainly ſend the reſt. The King ere he went from <hi>New-warke,</hi> as hee had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded this ſilken baſe theefe, in iuſtice to bee put to death, ſo in his beninge and gracious mercie, he giues life to all the other poore and wretched priſoners, clearing the Caſtle of them al. This deed of charitie done, before he left <hi>New-warke,</hi> he made theſe Knights.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iohn Parker.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Robert Bret.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Lewes Lewkener.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Francis Ducket.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Mumperſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Richard Warbirton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Richard Wigmore.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Edmond Foxe.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The 22. day being Fryday, his Maieſtie departed from <hi>New-warke,</hi> toward <hi>Beuer</hi> Caſtle, hunting all the way as he rode, ſauing that in the way he made theſe foure Knights, one being the Shiriffe of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinghamſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Roger Askoth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Sutton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iohn Stanhop.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Brian Laſſels.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:8733:17"/>
            <p>Sir <hi>Roger Askoth,</hi> high Shiriffe of <hi>Nottinghamſhire,</hi> being Knighted, tooke leaue of his Maieſtie, and Sir <hi>W. Pelham</hi> high Shiriffe of <hi>Lincolneſhire,</hi> receiued his Highneſſe, being gallantly appointed both with Horſe and men; diuers worſhipfull men of the ſame Countrey accompaing him, who conuoyed and gaurded his Maieſty to <hi>Beuer</hi> Caſtle, being the right Noble Earle of <hi>Rutlands:</hi> where his Highneſſe was not only royally, and moſt plentifully receiued, but with ſuch exceeding ioy of the good Earle, and his honourable Lady, that he tooke therein excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding pleaſure. And he approued his contentment in the morning, for before hee went to breake his faſt, he made theſe Knights whoſe names follow.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Oliuer Manners.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Willoughby.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Thomas Willoughby.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Gregorie Cromwell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir George Manners.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Henry Haſtings.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Pelham.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Philip Tyrright.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Valantine Browne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Roger Dalliſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Thomas Grantham.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iohn Zouche.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Iepſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Edward Askoth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Oliuer Digby.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Anthonie Markam.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Thomas Caue.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Turpin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iohn Ferres.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Henry Pagnam.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Richard Muſgraue.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Walter Chute.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Lambert.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Edward Roſſeter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Edward Comines.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Philip Sterley.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Edward Swift.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Baſile Brooke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Fairefaux.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Edward Buſh.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Edward Tyrright.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iohn Thorne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Nicholas Sanderſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Edward Littleton.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:8733:17"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Fompt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Thomas Beaumout.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Skeuington.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Henry Beaumont.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Philip Sharred.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iohn Tirril.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Edward Carre.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Richard Ogle.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Haman Swythcoate.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Hickman.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Fieldings.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Humfrey Conisby.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The 23. day being Satterday, after the making of theſe Knights, and hauing refreſhed himſelfe at breakfaſt, his Maieſty tooke kinde leaue of the Earle of <hi>Rutland,</hi> his Counteſſe, and the reſt, and ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward towards <hi>Burleigh,</hi> and by the way he dined at Sir <hi>Iohn Haringtons,</hi> where that worthy Knight made him moſt Royall entertainment.</p>
            <p>After dinner his Highneſſe remoued towards <hi>Burleigh,</hi> being neere <hi>Stanford</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire.</hi> His Maieſtie on the way was attended by many Lords and Knghts: and before his comming, there was prouided train-cents, and liue haires in baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, being carried to the heath, that made excellent ſport for his Maieſtie: all the way betweene Sir <hi>Iohn Haringtons</hi> and <hi>Stanford,</hi> ſir <hi>Iohns</hi> beſt hounds with good mouthes following the game, the King ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king great leiſure and pleaſure in the ſame.</p>
            <p>Vpon this heath, not farre from <hi>Stanford,</hi> there appeared to the number of an hundred high men that ſeemed like the <hi>Patagones,</hi> huge long fellowes, of twelue and fourteene foote high, that are repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to liue on the Mayne of <hi>Braſil,</hi> neere to the ſtreights of <hi>Megallant.</hi> The King at the firſt ſight wondered what they were, for that they ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looked horſe and man. But when all came to all,
<pb facs="tcp:8733:18"/>they proued a company of poore honeſt ſutors, all going vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> high ſtilts, preferring a petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt the Lady <hi>Hatton.</hi> What their requeſt was I know not, but his Maieſtie referred them till his comming to <hi>London,</hi> and ſo paſt on from thoſe gyants of the Fen, toward <hi>Stanford.</hi> Within halfe a myle whereof the Bailiffes and the reſt of the chiefe Towneſmen of <hi>Stanford,</hi> preſented a gift vnto his Maieſtie, which was gracioufly accepted: ſo rid he forward through the Towne in great ſtate, hauing the ſword borne before him, the people ioyfull on all partes to ſee him.</p>
            <p>When his Highneſſe came to <hi>Stanford</hi> bridge, the Shiriffe of <hi>Lincolnſhire</hi> humbly tooke his leaue, and departed greatly in the Kings grace. On the other part (the Towne ſtanding in two ſhires) ſtood readie the high Shiriffe of <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> braue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accompanied, and gallantly appointed with men and horſe, who receiued his Maieſtie and atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him to <hi>Burleigh,</hi> where his Highneſſe with all his traine were receiued with great magnificence, the houſe ſeeming ſo rich, as if it had beene furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed at the charges of an Emperour. Well, it was all too litle, his Maieſtie being worthy much more, being now the greateſt Chriſtian Monarke of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe as abſolute.</p>
            <p>The next day being Eaſter day, there Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched before his Highneſſe the Byſhoppe of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne,</hi> and the Sermon was no ſooner done, but all offices in the houſe were ſet open, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man might haue free acceſſe to Buttries, Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, Kitchins to eate and drinke in at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8733:18"/>
            <p>The next day being Monday the 25. of Aprill, his Highneſſe rode backe againe to ſir <hi>Iohn Haring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons:</hi> and by the way his Horſe fell with him, and very daungerouſly bruiſed his arme, to the great amazement and griefe of all them that were about his Maieſtie at that time. But he being of an inuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible courage, and his blood yet hotte, made light of it at the firſt: and being mounted againe, rode to ſir <hi>Iohn Haringtons,</hi> where hee continued that night.</p>
            <p>And on Tueſday morning, the paine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by his fall was ſo great, that he was not able to ride on horſebacke, but he turned from ſir <hi>Iohn Haringtons</hi> to take a Coach, wherein his Highneſſe returned to <hi>Burleigh,</hi> where he was Royallie en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained as before, but not with halfe that ioy, the report of his Maieſties hurt had diſturbed all the Court ſo much.</p>
            <p>The next day being Wedneſday the 27. day of Aprill, his Maieſtie remoued from <hi>Burleigh,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Maiſter <hi>Oliuer Cromwels,</hi> and in the way he dined at that worthy and worſhipfull Knights ſir <hi>Anthony Mildmayes,</hi> where nothing wanted in a ſubiects dutie to his Soueraigne: nor any thing in ſo potent a Soueraigne, to grace ſo loyall a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect.</p>
            <p>Dinner being moſt ſumptuouſly furniſhed, the Tables were newly couered with coſtly banquets, wherein euery thing that was moſt delitious for taſte, prooued more delicate, by the Arte that made it ſeeme beauteous to the eye. The Lady
<pb facs="tcp:8733:19"/>of the houſe, being one of the moſt excellent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectioners in <hi>England,</hi> though I confeſſe many Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable women very expert.</p>
            <p>Dinner and banket being paſt, and his Maieſtie at point to depart, ſir <hi>Anthonie,</hi> conſidering how his Maieſtie vouchſafed to honor him with his Roi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all preſence, preſented his Highneſſe with a gallant <hi>Barbary</hi> horſe, and a very rich ſaddle, with furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſutable thereunto: which his Maieſtie moſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly and thankfully accepted, and ſo taking his princely leaue, ſet forward on the way.</p>
            <p>In this remoue towards maiſter <hi>Oliuer Cromwels,</hi> did the people flocke in greater numbers, then in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny place Northward: though many before preaſt to ſee their Soueraigne, yet here the numbers mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed.</p>
            <p>This day, as his Maieſtie paſſed through a great common (which as the people there-about com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, ſir <hi>I. Spenſer</hi> of <hi>London</hi> hath very vncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble moleſted) moſt of the Countrey ioyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, beſeeching his Maieſtie that the Commons might bee laid open againe for the comfort of the poore Inhabiters there-about, which his Highneſſe moſt graciouſly promiſed ſhould be performed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their hearts deſire. And ſo with many benedictions of the comforted people hee paſſed on till he came within halfe a mile of maiſter <hi>Oliuer Cromwels,</hi> where met him the Bailiffe of <hi>Huntington,</hi> who made along Oration to his Maieſtie, and there deliuered him the Sword, which his Highneſſe gaue to the new releaſed Earle of <hi>Southampton,</hi> to beare before him.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8733:19"/>
            <p>O admirable worke of mercie, confirming the hearts of all true ſubiects in the good opinion of his Maieſties royall compaſſion: not alone to deliuer from the captiuitie ſuch high Nobilitie, but to vſe vulgarly with great fauours, not only him, but alſo the children of his late Honourable fellow in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe. Well, God haue glory that can ſend friends in the houre he beſt pleaſeth, to helpe them that truſt in him. But to the matter.</p>
            <p>His Maieſtie paſſed in State, the Earle of <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hampton</hi> bearing the Sword before him, as I before ſaid hee was appointed, to maiſter <hi>Oliuer Cromwels</hi> houſe, where his Maieſty and all his followers, with all commers whatſoeuer, had ſuch entertainment, as the like had not beene ſeene in any place before, ſince his firſt ſetting forward out of <hi>Scotland.</hi> There was ſuch plentie and varietie of meates, ſuch diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of wines, &amp; thoſe not riffe ruffe, but euer the beſt of the kinde, and the ſellers open at any mans pleaſure. And if it were ſo common with wine, there is little queſtion but the Buttries for beere and ale were more common: yet in neither was there difference: for who euer entred the houſe, which to no man was denyed, taſted what they had a minde too, and after a taſte found fulneſſe, no man like a man, being denied what he would call for.</p>
            <p>As this bountie was held backe to none within the houſe, ſo for ſuch poore people as would not preaſe in, there were open beere-houſes erected, wherein there was no want of bread and beefe, for the comfort of the pooreſt creatures. Neither was this prouiſion for the litle time of his Maieſties ſtay,
<pb facs="tcp:8733:20"/>but it was made ready 14. daies, &amp; after his Highnes departure diſtributed to as many as had mind to it.</p>
            <p>There attended alſo at maiſter <hi>Oliuer Cromwels,</hi> the heads of the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> all clad in Scarlet Gownes and corner Cappes; who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing preſence of his Maieſtie, there was made a moſt learned and eloquent Oration in Latine, welcomming his Maieſtie, as alſo intreating the confirmation of their Charter and Priuiledges, which his Maieſtie moſt willingly and freely gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. They alſo preſented his Maieſtie with diuers bookes publiſhed in commendation of our late gracious <hi>Queene,</hi> all which was moſt graciouſly accepted of his Highneſſe. Alſo Maiſter <hi>Cromwell</hi> preſented his Maieſtie with many rich and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble gifts, as a very great, and a very faire wrought ſtanding Cup of gold, goodly horſes, floate and deepe mouthed Houndes, diuers Hawkes of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent wing, and at the remoue gaue 50. pound, amongſt his Maieſties Officers.</p>
            <p>Vpon the 29. day being Fryday, after his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe had broke his faſt, he tooke kinde and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous leaue of Maiſter <hi>Oliuer Cromwell,</hi> and his vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lady, late Widow, to that Noble and opulent Knight, <hi>Seigniour Horatio Paulo Vicino.</hi> Thence with many regall thankes for his entertainment, hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted to <hi>Roiſton.</hi> And as he paſſed through <hi>Cod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancheſter,</hi> a Towne cloſe by <hi>Huntington,</hi> the Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffes of the Towne with their brethren met him, and acknowledged their alleageance. There, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoying him through their Towne, they preſented him, with threeſcore and ten Teeme of horſe all tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb facs="tcp:8733:20"/>too faire new ploughs, in ſhew of their Husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie. Which, while his Maieſtie being very wel de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with the ſight, demanded why they offered him ſo many horſes and ploughes: he was reſolued that it was their auncient cuſtome, whenſoeuer any king of <hi>England</hi> paſſed through their towne, ſo to preſent his Excellence. Beſides they added, that they held their lands by that tenure, being the kings tenants: his Maieſtie not only tooke well in worth their good mindes, but bad them vſe well their ploughes, being glad hee was Land-lord of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good Husbandmen in one Towne. I truſt his Highneſſe, when hee knowes well the wrong, will take order for thoſe, as her Maieſtie began, that turne plough-land to Paſtorage: and where many good Husbandmen dwelt, there is now nothing left, but a great houſe without fire: the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly at ſoioure neere <hi>London,</hi> &amp; for the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and ploughes, hee only maintaines a Sheepe-heard and his dog. But what do I talking of ſheepe when I am to follow the geſtes of a King. I will leaue them and their woluiſh lords, that haue eaten vp poore Husbandmen like ſheepe, and proceede where I left.</p>
            <p>His Maieſtie being paſt <hi>Godmancheſter,</hi> held on his way towardes <hi>Royston,</hi> and drawing neere the Towne, the Shiriffe of <hi>Huntingtonſhire</hi> humbly tooke his leaue: and there hee was receiued by that worthy Knight, <hi>Sir Edward Deny,</hi> high Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe of <hi>Hartfordſhire,</hi> attended vpon by a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly companie of proper men, beeing in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſeuen ſcore, ſutably apparelled, their Liueries
<pb facs="tcp:8733:21"/>blew Coates with ſleeues parted in the middeſt, buttoned behinde in Ierkin faſhion, &amp; white dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, and hats and feathers, and all of them mounted on horſes with red ſaddles.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Edward</hi> after his humble dutie done, preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Maieſtie with a gallant horſe, a riche ſaddle, and ſurniture correſpondent to the ſame, being of great value, which his Maieſtie accepted very gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly, and cauſed him to ride on the ſame before him. This worthy Knight being of a deliuer ſpirit, and agil body, quickly mounted, managing the gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant beaſt, with neate and eiduing workmanſhip, being in a rich ſute of a yellow dun colour, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what neere the colour of the horſe &amp; the furniture. And thus in braue manner he conducted his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie to one maiſter <hi>Chesters</hi> houſe, where his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe lay that night, on his owne kingly charge.</p>
            <p>The 30. day being Satterday, his Maieſtie tooke his iourney towards <hi>Standon,</hi> to <hi>Sir Thomas Sadlers,</hi> and by the way the Byſhop of <hi>London</hi> met him; at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended on by a ſeemely company of Gentlemen in tawny Coates and chaines of gold. At <hi>Sir Thomas Sadlers,</hi> his Maieſtie was royally entertained, for himſelfe and his Kingly traine: nothing being wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the beſt deſired, nor that the meaneſt could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund. There his Maieſtie ſtayed Sunday, before whom the Byſhop of <hi>London</hi> preached.</p>
            <p>His Maieſtie now drawing neere to <hi>London,</hi> the numbers of people more and more increaſed, aſwel of Nobilitie, Gentrie, Citizens, Countrey-people, and all, aſwell of degree, as of no degree; ſo great a deſire had the Noble, that they preaſt with the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble
<pb facs="tcp:8733:21"/>to ſee their Soueraigne. This being the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of their deſires, that the better ſort either in blood or of conceit, came to obſerue and ſerue; the other to ſee and wonder.</p>
            <p>The firſt of May being Munday, his Maieſtie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued to <hi>Sir Henrie Cocks,</hi> being nine miles from <hi>Sir Thomas Sadlers,</hi> where prouiſion for his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and his Royall traine, was ſo abundant, that there was no man of what condition ſoeuer, but had what his appetite deſired. For his Maieſties priuate and moſt to bee reſpected entertainment, it was ſuch as miniſtred his Highneſſe great content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Continuing there but one night, and depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the next day, honoured the good Knight for his greater expenſes.</p>
            <p>The 3. of May being Tueſday, his Maieſty tooke his iourney towards <hi>Theobals,</hi> a houſe belonging to Lord <hi>Robert Cecill,</hi> and about foure miles diſtant from <hi>Sir Henry Cocks,</hi> where met him the Lord <hi>Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> the Lord <hi>Treaſurer,</hi> the Lord <hi>Admiral,</hi> with moſt of the Nobilitie of the Land, and Counſell of Eſtate, who were graciouſly receiued. At which time the Lord <hi>Keeper</hi> made a moſt graue, learned, briefe and pithie Oration to his Maieſtie. To which his Highnes anſwered with great grace and prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſdome.</p>
            <p>At this houſe, there met his Maieſtie, all, or the moſt part of the old ſeruants and officers in Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, of our late Royall Miſtreſſe <hi>Queene Elizabeth,</hi> and with them the guarde of his Maieſties body, all of them being courteouſly receiued to their owne content. Alſo in this houſe of <hi>Theobals,</hi> his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie
<pb facs="tcp:8733:22"/>made diuers Noblemen of <hi>Scotland,</hi> of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable priuie Counſell. <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>The Duke of <hi>Lennox.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Earle of <hi>Mar.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The L. <hi>Home. Sir George Home,</hi> Treaſurer of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iames Elphingſton,</hi> Secretarie to the King.</item>
               <item>The L. of <hi>Kinloſſe,</hi> now M. of his Maieſties Rolles.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Alſo of the Engliſh Nobilitie, he made theſe of his ſecret and Honourable Counſell.</p>
            <list>
               <item>The Lord <hi>Henrie Howard.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Lord <hi>Thomas Howard,</hi> who was alſo made there, Lord Chamberlaine.</item>
               <item>The Lord <hi>Monioy.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>His Maieſtie ſtayed at <hi>Theobals,</hi> 4. dayes; where, to ſpeake of Lord <hi>Roberts</hi> coſt to entertaine him, were but to imitate Geographers, that ſets a little round o. for a mighty prouince: words being hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly able to expreſſe what was done there in deed, conſidering the multitude that thither reſorted beſide the traine, none going thence vnſatiſfied. At <hi>Theobals,</hi> his Maieſtie made theſe Knights.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Killegraue.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Francis Barinton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Rouland Litton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Peters.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iohn Brograue.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Cooke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Henry Capell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Harbert Crofts.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Edward Grenill.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Henry Butler.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Henrie Maynard.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Richard Spencer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iohn Leuenthrope.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Nicholas Stanhop.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Thomas Popeblunt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Richard Iefford.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:8733:22"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Thomas Medcalfe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Emanuel Capel.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Smith.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> Ferres.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Robert Bitton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Vincine Skinner.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Hugh Beeſton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iohn Leigh.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Thomas Byſhop.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> Lewes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iaruis Elues.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Robert Barker.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The 7. of May being Satterday, his Maieſtie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued from <hi>Theobals,</hi> towardes <hi>London,</hi> riding through the Medowes, where within two miles on this ſide of <hi>Waltham, Sir Henry Deny</hi> diſcharged his followers, and there maiſter <hi>Swinnerton,</hi> one of the Shiriffes of <hi>London,</hi> accompanied with the Shiriffe of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> met his Maiſtie, with 60. men in Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie cloakes, where an eloquent and learned Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was made to his Highneſſe.</p>
            <p>Beſides theſe men in Liuery cloakes that atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Shiriffe, all well mounted on gallant horſes, moſt of the Shiriffes Officers attended him, who conducted his Maieſty within two miles of <hi>London.</hi> And at <hi>Stanford</hi> hil, the Lord <hi>Maior</hi> of <hi>London</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented him with the Sword and Keyes of the Citie, with whom were the Knights and Aldermen in skarlet gownes and great chaines of golde about their neckes, with all the chiefe Officers and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the Cittie. Beſides 500. Citizens, all very well mounted, clad in Veluet coates and chaines of gold, with the chiefe Gentlemen of the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, who made a gallant ſhew to entertaine their Soueraigne.</p>
            <p>There alſo met his Maieſtie, all his Officers of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, as Sergea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts at Armes with their rich maces, the
<pb facs="tcp:8733:23"/>Heraulds with their coate of Armes, and Trumpet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, euery one in their order and due place. The Duke of <hi>Lennox</hi> bearing the ſword of Honour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford his Maieſtie, and ſo his Highneſſe paſſed on, in Royall and imperiall manner.</p>
            <p>At this time, that honourable olde Knight, <hi>Sir Henry Leigh</hi> met with his Maieſtie, being attended by 60. gallant men, well mounted on faire horſes, thirtie of them being great horſes, many of his men hauing chaines of gold, the reſt wearing yellow ſearfes embrodered with theſe wordes: <hi>Constantia &amp; fide.</hi> To this old Knight, his Maieſtie ſpake very louingly, and ſo pacedthrough his troupes very well pleaſed.</p>
            <p>The multitudes of people in high wayes, fieldes, medowes, cloſes and on trees were ſuch, that they couered the beautie of the fieldes, and ſo greedy were they to behold the countenance of the King, that with much vnrulineſſe they iniured and hurt one another, ſome euen hazarded to the daunger of death: but as vnciuill as they were among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, all the way as his Maieſtie paſt with ſhoutes and cryes, and caſting vp of hattes (of which many neuer returned into the owners hands) he paſſed by them ouer the the fields, and came in at the backe ſide of the <hi>Charterhouſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thither being come, hee was moſt Royally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued and entertained, by the Lord <hi>Thomas Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> where was ſuch abundance of prouiſion of all manner of things, that greater could not bee: both of rare wild ſoules, and many rare and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary bankets, to the great liking of his Maieſtie,
<pb facs="tcp:8733:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>and contentment of the whole trayne. He lay there three nights, in which time the Lords of Counſell often reſorted thither, and ſate vpon their ſerious affaires. At his departure he made diuers Knights, whoſe names are theſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Charles Haward.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Ambroſe Willoughby.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Edward Haward.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Hastings.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Giles Alington.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> Verney.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iohn Thinne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Willia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Fitz-williams.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Carrell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Edmond Bakon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Francis Anderſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iohn Pountney.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Edward Darcy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> Sidenham.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iohn Tuston.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Thomas Griffin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Valentine Knightly.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> Wiſeman.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Thomas Ayleffe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> Cromer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Thomas Rowſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> Rodney.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Henry Vaughan.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iohn Smyth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> Hamman.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Thomas Meade.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Euſebius Iſham.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iohn Cowper.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Robert Winkfield.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Thomas Ioſling.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Henry Goodericke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Maximillian Dalliſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Crape.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir George Fleetwood.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Peter Euers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Henry Cleere.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Francis Wolly.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Arthur Mannering.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Edward Waterhouſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> Twiſaldon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Hatton Cheeke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> Goring.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Robert Townſend.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Hynde.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Sandes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Robert Cotton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Oliuer Luke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Thoms Kneuet.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Henry Sackford.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Edwine Sands.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iohn Abſley.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Fleetwood.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:8733:24"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Walter Mildmay.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Edward Lewkener.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Miles Sands.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr William Kingſwell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Thomas Kempe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Edward Tirrel.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Thomas Ruſſel.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Richard Touchburn.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Thomas Cornwell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Richard Farmer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr William Stafford.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Thomas Carrel.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Edward Carrel.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Thomas Palmer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Iohn Newdigate.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr George Rawleigh.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Thomas Bewford.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr William Lower.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Charles Fairefaux.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Henry Sidney.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr George Haruey.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Henry Crippes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Iohn Himmegham.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr William Bowger.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Ieremie Weſtam.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Edmond Boyer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Nicholas Halſeworth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Iohn Gennings.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Ambroſe Turwell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Iohn Luke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr William Dormer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Richar Saunders.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iohn Shearley.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Thomas Wayneman.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Goddard Pempton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Thomas Mettame.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Edm. Bellingham.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iohn Harington.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Edward Harington.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Dyer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr William Dyer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Walter Mountague.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Guy Palme.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> Aſhley.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Thomas Vackathell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Thomas Stukeley.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Edward Watſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Thomas Preſton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr William Leeke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Thomas Cornwalles.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Edward Francis.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Hugh Loſſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Lygon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Thomas le Groſſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iohn Taskerow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Thomas Fowler.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Euſebius Andrew.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Edward Andrew.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr William Kingſwel.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Robert Lucie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir William Walter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Iohn Cuts.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Richard blunt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Anthonie Deerings.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:8733:24"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr H. Vaughan.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Iohn Carew.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Edward Apſley.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Bartram Boomer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr William Alford.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Robert Lee.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Thomas Beaumont.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Robert Markam.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Francis Caſtilon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr George Sauil.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr George Martham.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Arthur Attie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Pexal Brockhurſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Iohn Waſhall.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Robert Cleueland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syr Richard Farmer.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Vpon Wedneſday the 11. of May, his Maieſtie ſet forward from the <hi>Charterhouſe,</hi> to the Towre of <hi>London,</hi> in going quietly on horſebacke to <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall,</hi> where he tooke Barge: hauing ſhot the Bridge, his preſent landing was expected at Towre ſtayres, but it pleaſed his Highneſſe to paſſe the Towre ſtaires towards S. <hi>Katherines,</hi> and there ſtayed on the water to ſee the Ordinance on the white towre (commonly called <hi>Iulius Caeſars</hi> Towre) being in number 20. peeces, with the great Ordinance on Towre wharfe, being in number one hundred, and Chalmers, to the number of 130. diſcharged and ſhot off. Of which, all ſeruices were ſo ſufficiently performed by the gunners, that a peale of ſo good order was neuer heard before: which was moſt commendable to all ſorts, and very acceptable to the King. Then his Royall perſon arriued at his owne ſtaires, ſo called the Kings ſtaires, and with him theſe Nobles, beſides other gallant Gentlemen of worthy note: <hi>Viz.</hi> The Lord <hi>Admiral,</hi> the Earle of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> the Lord of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> Lord <hi>Thomas Howard,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>At his comming vp the ſtaires, the Sword was preſented to his Maieſtie, by <hi>Syr Thomas Conisby,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:8733:25"/>Gentleman Vſher of his priuie Chamber, &amp; by the King deliuered to the Duke of <hi>Lennox,</hi> who bare it before him into the Towre. Vpon the ſtaires the Gentleman Porter deliuered the keies of the towre to the Leiutenant of the Towre, &amp; the Leiutenant preſented them accordingly to the Kings Maieſtie: who moſt graciouſly acknowledged the moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſcharge of the loyall and moſt great truſt put in him, ſo taking him about the necke, redeliuered them againe. After his repoſe in the Towre ſome houre, it was his Maieſties pleaſure, to ſee ſome Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, as the Armorie, the Wardrobe, the rich Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillerie, and the Church. And after for recreation, he walked in the garden, &amp; ſo reſted for that night.</p>
            <p>The next day being Thurſday, &amp; the 12. of May, hee ſaw the Ordinance houſe, and after that the Mynt-houſes, and laſt of all the Lyons.</p>
            <p>The next day being Fryday, the 13. of May, he made theſe Lords and Knights following: <hi>Viz.</hi> in his preſence Chamber, before dinner.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Lord <hi>Cecill</hi> of <hi>Eſemdon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lord <hi>Sidney</hi> of <hi>Penſhourſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lord <hi>Knowles</hi> of <hi>Graſcy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lord <hi>Wotton</hi> of <hi>Guarleyes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iohn Deanie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Iohn Traue.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Thomas Smyth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Thomas Hubbard.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And after Noone in the Gallerie-
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir William Dethicke.</hi> Garter.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir Robert Markam.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir George Merton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir Edmond Bolt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir Thomas Paiton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir Dauid Fowles.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir William Gardner.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:8733:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
